# Efosa Idemudia Odiase

Houston, TX 77056 7042870362 efosa.dba@gmail.com

## **Professional Summary**

Production Database Administrator with 9+ years' experience supporting production databases (Banking, Finance, Healthcare, Insurance, Retail). Areas of expertise include Database high availability, maintenance, security, backup and restores, performance and query tuning, migration, upgrade, patching, scripting, Disaster recovery and PowerShell automation. Team player, collaborative, self-motivated, excellent communication skills, analytical mindset, efficient problem solving, decision making abilities. Experience Working on Azure and AWS Cloud.

### **PROJECT**

- Recently completed Migration of over 100 Databases to Azure SQL, Azure managed instance and Azure VM.
- Coordinated SQL Server AlwaysOn HA/DR Drill By Simulating Failover Of Over 50 AlwaysOn AG from primary to secondary.
- Successfully Decommissioned 50 SQL Server instances from versions 2008 to 2012 in response to Microsoft's End-of-life support, ensuring system compliance and mitigating potential security risks.
- Recently Migrated over 100 Databases from company legacy servers (version 2012), to New build SQL Servers (version 2019 and 2022)

## **Professional Experience**

**SQL Database Administrator**, 07/2018 — Current

#### **Microdevelopment Consulting Limited**

- Provisioning Databases and configuring appropriate HA/DR strategy based on the RTO/RPO objective of the organization
- Manage over 500 databases and VLDB across multiple data centers
- Enhance database performance, perform restores, implement recovery procedures, and conduct regular health checks and system backups
- Carries out performance tuning task on a regular basis on issues ranging from query tuning to index optimization, TempDB issues, to IO, High CPU usage, severe blocking, long running query, AlwaysOn out of sync, mirroring out of sync, log shipping out of sync
- Involve in Technical decisions for Business requirement, Interaction with Business Analysts, Client team, Development team, Capacity planning and upgrading of SQL Servers
- Expert in configuring, Maintaining, and troubleshooting Log shipping, Mirroring, AlwaysOn Availability Groups, replication, SQL server Failover cluster on same and multiple subnets
- Configured DR solution with Transaction Replication from Distribution Server with multiple Update table subscriptions
- Migrated SQL Server from on premises to Azure SQL Database
- Responsible for setting up and maintaining High Availability and Disaster Recovery Solutions and large-scale database migrations from SQL Server 2005 to SQL Server 2012R2, 2014, 2016 and 2019
- Monitors daily, weekly, Monthly, and quarterly Maintenance Task, ensuring that its successful and resolves any issues when it fails
- Performs Database consistency checks with DBCC, Defrag, Index tuning and monitored error logs.
- Supports Reporting Servers (SSRS), Integration Services (SSIS), Analysis Services (SSAS).
- Using SSIS, building high performance data integration solutions, including extraction, transformation, and load (ETL) packages for data warehousing.
- Weekly Patching of Standalone and Cluster instances.
- Performs Physical and Logical Data Modelling for databases of varied sizes including VLDBs.
- Configure DR solution with Transaction Replication from Distribution Server with multiple Update table

- subscriptions.
- Assists SQL server prime customers with configuration, administration, implementation and troubleshooting for business workflow with log shipping mechanism.
- Resolves SQL server problems in conformance with SLAs, which involves in depth knowledge of SQL server architecture, connectivity, replication, backup/restore, security and continuous improvement.
- Performs Database Refresh tasks from production to Development and Staging Servers.
- Manages permissions and security, performs security tasks like Grant, Revoke permissions for security tasks.
- Provides On-Call support to Mission Critical Environments.
- Use Monitoring tools like Fog Light, Red Gate, Idera, Spotlight for monitoring my environment.
- Use Ticketing System tools like Service Now and JIRA to Speed up and Deliver key DBA tasks.
- Resolve performance issues with PerfMon, used SQL profiler, and NetMon for monitoring and performing network throughput issues.
- Managed SQL Server Backup with Third party tools such as Commvault, Rubrik, IBM Spectrum-Protect.
- Collaborated closely with development teams to integrate database version control using Redgate SQL Source Control, aligning database changes with application updates and fostering a cohesive DevOps culture.

### **SQL Server Database Administrator**, 01/2014 — 07/2018

## **Zenith IT Consulting Services LTD**

- Monitored SQL health checks and identified issues and fixed them
- Used SQL Indexes for improving query performance, lower storage, and maintenance cost
- MS SQL Server design, Development and administration using SQL Server 2005 2014 database environments
- Used Optimization and monitoring tools such as SQL Profiler, Dynamic Management Views (DMVs), SentryOne SQL Sentry, Dynatrace, PRTG Network Monitor, Windows Performance Monitor for monitoring and tuning SQL Server performance.
- Implemented Installation, Configuration and Upgrading of SQL Server
- Automated administrative tasks like creating jobs and schedules, alerts using SQL Server Agent monitoring and troubleshooting jobs, event notifications using Database Mail
- Maintained server security by assigning logins, server and database roles and server permissions
- Implemented disaster prevention and recovery strategies and supported High Availability features like Clustering, Always On, Log Shipping, Database Mirroring and Replication
- Maintained database response times in 24X7 production environment and proactively generated reports
- Planned and Implemented database backup/restore and disaster recovery
- Implemented Log Shipping from Primary to Standby servers
- Created and maintained SQL objects like Tables, Views, Stored Procedure, Constraints and User defined functions
- Responsible for installing and maintaining SSIS, SSRS, and Power BI.

## **Project Support Analyst**, 01/2013 — 12/2013

## **Skye Bank PLC**

- Organized and facilitated key decision-making sessions while capturing minutes and tracking actions
- Developed and managed the weekly project plan which pictorially represents all the key highlights of the project on a weekly basis
- Developed detailed planning schedules using MS projects which depicts key activities and critical paths required to achieve key milestones
- Provided support to project managers and managed key onshore and offshore stakeholders
- Accurate capture of information for input into various tracking spreadsheets and databases.

## **Junior Business Analyst**, 10/2012 — 01/2013

#### **Conduent Business Services**

- Conducted business and system analysis to determine specific needs and documented these as requirements functional and non-functional
- Gathered, analyzed, and documented functional and non-functional requirements
- Developed test scripts and conducted User Acceptance Testing (UAT)
- Obtained stakeholder sign off for business requirements and completed solution design

• Effectively championed the risk and issues on log management for the project.

# **Education and Training**

09/2012 Benson Idahosa University
Bachelor of Science Accounting
10/2013 Complete Computers (Lagos)
Certificate of Completion SQL Server Database Administration
01/2023 Technation (US)
Certificate of Competition AZURE Fundamentals
05/2010 Complete Computers (Lagos)
Certificate of Completion Microsoft Office

## References

References available upon request.